Wood Cowan Papers
Wood Cowan Papers
1928-1955
Cowan, Wood
18 linear ft.
Original cartoons, illustrations, sketches, proofs, clippings, published material, scripts and correspondence.
2655684
Biographical History
Woodson Messick Cowan (1889-1977), commonly known as Wood Cowan, was an American cartoonist, illustrator and painter.
Originally from Algona, Iowa, Cowan attended the University of Iowa before pursuing art studies at the Art Institute of Chicago. Cowan started in the newspaper business as a sports writer and cartoonist for the George Matthew Adams Syndicate in New York City (1920-1927). During this period he produced sports cartoons and worked on a number of various comic strip titles including Vivian the Vamp, Them Were the Days and Mom 'n' Pop. In 1946, Cowan briefly worked on George Ahern's comic strip Our Boarding House, featuring the popular Major Hoople character. Beginning in 1949, Cowan served as editorial cartoonist for the Bridgeport (Conn.) Evening Post (1949-1959), and then for the New Haven Register (1960-1969).
Wood Cowan was also a prolific illustrator and painter throughout his career. He contributed work to a wide variety of popular magazines including the New Yorker and Argosy, and illustrated numerous book publications. In addition, his paintings were featured in gallery exhibitions in Westport, Conn. (1964), Darien, Conn. (1968), Norwalk, Conn. (1970) and Jekyll Island, Ga. (1972).
A long time resident of Connecticut, Cowan served two terms in the state legislature there (1953-1957) and did a single term as First Selectman for the town of Weston (1957-1959).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Wood Cowan Papers consists primarily of original cartoons and cartoon proofs. The entire range of Cowan's cartoon work is represented including approximately 50 original sports cartoons, 300 original editorial cartoons and hundreds of original cartoons from many of the comic strip titles that Cowan worked on—Vivian the Vamp, Carrie and Her Car, Them Were the Days, Mom 'n' Pop, Sissy, and others. The collection also contains a broad sampling of Cowan's magazine and book illustration work (original sketches, drawings, proofs and clippings). This work includes his Teen Tips series, Flying (A) Andy panels, Western Greats panels and sketches for Iowa Cracker Barrel, his tribute to his Iowa prairie roots. In addition, the collection includes some pieces of correspondence, two typed scripts related to Keen Trailer stories, and many other miscellaneous sketches, drawings and cartoons.
Arrangement of the Collection
Comic strips and titled illustration work are grouped together by title and arranged in chronological order. Sports and editorial cartoons are grouped separately and arranged in alphabetical order by title. There are multiple packages that contain loose groupings of miscellaneous materials. Please note that a complete inventory and reprocessing of the collection is pending. Contact the Repository for more information.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Art -- Illustrators; Cowan, Wood.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Illustration of books -- 20th century.; Illustrators -- United States.; Sports -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Illustrations.; Cartoonists.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Wood Cowan, 1966 and Thaddeus Cowan, 1977.
Inventory
- Package 1
  - Miscellaneous cartoons [8 cartoons]
    - 1928, 1931, 1933, 1934, 1937, 1939 (2), n.d.(1)
- Package 2
  - Wanted Dead or Alive [posters, 63 copies]
- Package 3
  - Western Greats [64 cartoons, 1 book]
- Package 4
  - The Berry's Family Album
    - 69 cartoons - 1942
    - 29 cartoons - 1942
    - 12 newspaper proofs - 1942
- Package 5
  - Miscellaneous drawings and cartoons [39 items]
- Package 6
  - Major Hoople - drawings and proofs
  - Cradled on Main Street - drawings
  - Some People Can't Remember Names
  - Miscellaneous cartoons
  - Cracker Barrel - sketches
- Package 7
  - Puppet Show
- Package 8
  - Keen Trailer (late 1940s) [14 panels and 2 typewritten scripts about stories]
  - Dr. Merrywell - Family Doctor (early 1950s) [7 page proofs, 5 negative photocopies]
  - Marty McGee (1940s) [14 cartoons]
- Package 9
  - Oh, Diana!
    - 12/17/1948 - 01/08/1949 [10 cartoon panels]
    - 10/06/1947 - 12/20/1947 [25 page proofs]
- Package 10
  - Miscellaneous cartoons (1940s) [1 scrapbook]
- Package 11
  - Miscellaneous cartoons [5 cartoons]
- Package 13
  - Windy Winters (circa 1930) [1 scrapbook]
- Package 13
  - Miscellaneous cartoons (early 1920s) [40 cartoons]
  - Athletic Al [1 cartoon]
  - Auto Bugs and Buggies [14 cartoons]
  - Bonehead Bowlers [3 cartoons]
  - The Busy Bowlers Club [1 cartoon]
  - Carrie and Her Car [2 cartoons]
  - The Stove League [4 cartoons]
  - Such is Golf [10 cartoons]
  - Vivian the Vamp [54 cartoons]
- Package 14
  - Sports cartoons (1922-1923)
    - Baseball reduces crime [1 cartoon]
    - Big league recruits [4 cartoons]
    - Coach Rockne [1 cartoon]
    - Come back champions [1 cartoon]
    - Gameness [1 cartoon]
    - I'll tell the world [1 cartoon]
    - In the spotlight of sport [22 cartoons]
    - The 'J' Fighters of the Squared Circle [1 cartoon]
    - The kick off [1 cartoon]
    - The left hand in sports [1 cartoon]
    - Legs [1 cartoon]
    - Making the fans laugh [1 cartoon]
    - Nobody home [1 cartoon]
    - Out for a home run record [1 cartoon]
    - Passing of the pop bottle [1 cartoon]
    - Playing against a stacked deck [1 cartoon]
    - University football captains [12 cartoons]
    - Weight vs. speed [1 cartoon]
- Package 15
  - Teen Tips (late 1940s)
    - 225 panels
    - 3 panel proofs
- Package 16
  - Flying (A) Andy (1940-1950s)
    - 130 magazine clippings
    - 3 panel proofs
- Package 17
  - Sports Thrills [40 items]
  - Scrapbook
  - Baseball's biggest boner
  - First American to win a British golf title
  - McGovern lost but he won
  - When a horse's nose was worth a million
  - The last charge of the old polo brigade
- Package 18
  - Editorial Cartoons A-L [99 cartoons]
    - A tap now—or 'The rap' later?
    - All the old pump needs is a little priming
    - An expert on our biggest problem
    - —and he'll take off bag and baggage!
    - And this isn't even the first team!
    - Any New Haven street corner
    - Anybody's ball?
    - Anything else we can do for you fellows?
    - April shower
    - Are other nations going to make our laws?
    - Are there gonna be any parks, Mister?
    - At the campaign crossroads
    - Barnum Festival
    - Beat the drums!
    - Better make those two threads stronger
    - Better not go too far, boys
    - Big shots in the dark
    - Boiling water was then poured in the trough from kettles hung on poles nearby
    - Build that dam higher!
    - But, Mother! We'd rather do it ourselves
    - Buying thru highways on the installment plan, or 'Give and Take'
    - Can't hold back progress
    - Checking the children on next year's route
    - Come on, step into line
    - Congressman Al Morano:
    - Count your blessings
    - Cruel and inhuman treatment
    - Dangerous curve ahead—
    - Design for health
    - Dig deeper
    - Dig those dollars!
    - Does Westport want this forever?
    - Don't kill Santa Claus!
    - The end of a successful voyage
    - Every accommodation-always a warm welcome here
    - Fence him out
    - Fill for the thruway means deep water for shipping (One hand helps the other)
    - Fill it and push it over the top
    - Five reasons
    - Flyin' high
    - For this I give thanks
    - A forward pass that should be declared out of bounds
    - Fruit of the tree
    - Future spending
    - Gates open to link Connecticut and New York
    - Get in step-join the Big Parade
    - Get rid of these extra gadgets. All we need is a car that'll take us places
    - Get your ammunition here, folks!
    - A gigantic sponge
    - Give him protection
    - Give him the full treatment
    - The gobblins will get you
    - Good advice
    - Has anyone got a peace-pipe?
    - Headlines and haircuts
    - He coming bag and pocket book(?)
    - He looks pretty healthy
    - Heh! One of you guys grab that string!!
    - He's been a good boy
    - He's in for another surprise, too
    - He's in the high income bracket
    - Hey! Open the door, it's Richard again!
    - The Hoarder
    - He's loaded!
    - Help!
    - Help keep her hands filled
    - Hey, take it easy! Remember my life is in your hands
    - How Connecticut highways are built
    - Hum-m-m. How does that sound?
    - I could pay for it
    - If I had t'find a place t'park in this town I'd never be able to make deliveries
    - If you fellows don't get your work done, you'll have to stay after school
    - I'll take him in the first round
    - In the past year
    - It Came Upon a Midnight Clear
    - It means a lot to him
    - It was ever thus
    - It's a late planting season
    - It's been cold outside
    - Just a sprinkle
    - Keep 'em dancing
    - Keep on rolling motor wheels
    - Kick off to a winning goal
    - Last year's skate just won't fit
    - (the above two are Kowalski's senatorial ambitions)
    - Leading the parade
    - Let Grand-paw decide
    - Let's do a little horn tooting
    - Let's do some selling ourselves
    - Lets get some real use out of it
    - Let's get that relief road built
    - Let's join the parade
    - Let's leave the hole to the bulldozers
    - Let's ring that bell
    - The life and achievements of Igor I Sikorsky
    - The light that You must not fail
    - Log jam
    - Log jam in our Federal Courts
    - Looks like brighter days ahead
- Package 19
  - Editorial Cartoons M-Y [94 cartoons]
    - Making it hard to deliver the goods
    - The modern Simon Legree
    - More at home would help
    - More elbow room
    - Move over, boys
    - The moving finger writes—
    - Must we come to this!
    - My, how you've grown!
    - New Year's resolutions
    - New Year's taxes
    - No more poultry on the highway
    - Now for the House and Senate!
    - OK'd all around
    - One more reason to hurry the construction of the Nutmeg Turnpike
    - One way traffic
    - Our own coronation
    - Out to make friends and influence people
    - Over the river—or through the woods?
    - Propaganda platform
    - Putting Connecticut on the international map
    - The red carpet for the Vice President
    - (the above two are Quit triffling, boys, there's work to be done)
    - Retrieving the Old Skimmer
    - Riding a pot-holder, or a magic carpet?
    - Road-block
    - Same tangle
    - Scenic Housatonic route would solve this problem
    - Send old toys to the Westport Junior Womans Club
    - She just keeps traveling along
    - The ship and the bottle-neck
    - Sit down! The majority oppose
    - Sifting 'em out - Running 'em through the sieve
    - Smoke rings the school bell
    - Something's got to be done about this!!
    - Something's got to give and soon
    - The sooner we have it the better
    - Sounds like a reasonable request
    - Speaker Sam Rayburn
    - Special this week —polio shots
    - Special this week—polio shots - only 50t
    - Start planning now
    - A step in the right direction
    - Step inside gentleman let me show you what New Haven has to offer you
    - Step right up boys, it's your money I'm passing out
    - Step up and—ring the bell
    - Stepping into the picture
    - Stop the run
    - Take your choice
    - Teeing off at Jekyll
    - Thanks, pal!!
    - That arm has a lot of muscle
    - That taxi's at the door
    - They both hold the same amount of water
    - They're both loaded
    - Time for rebuilding—all around
    - Time to start the sweeping
    - Time to trim his sails
    - Things look purty peaceful across the river
    - This is REALLY spooky!
    - This happens—and who is to blame?
    - And this was to be a spring clean-up job?
    - The thundering herd
    - To Helen, with affection from Wood Cowan
    - Two big improvements for the South End
    - An unseasonal dream
    - Up—and away!
    - Water over the dam [2 cartoons]
    - We aren't going to let anything stand in our way to get you down here—and quick!!
    - We do need that thruway bridge
    - We must fill in the valleys
    - We need the thruway for traffic relief, and YOU back the highway commissioner ... OR ELSE!!
    - We'll all reap the harvest
    - Welcome
    - Welcome City Hall
    - A welcome shot in the arm
    - Welcome Stranger
    - Welfare chiseler
    - We'll bet on the horse
    - Well, where DO you want the expressway to go?
    - Were going places!
    - Westport schoolmarm
    - Westport traffic puzzle
    - What next, little man?
    - Without your help someone gets left out
    - Which one reflects the good student
    - Win—Place—Show—
    - Women of Connecticut
    - Wood Cowan sketches some of those attending the G.O.P. Convention
    - Wrapping the Christmas packages
    - Ya-hoo, school's out!
    - You are now entering New York
    - You are the people I want to talk to!!
    - You can't lose your shadow
    - You have TWO years to solve these
    - The youngsters want a ride in Daddy's car
- Package 20
  - Untitled Editorial Cartoons [99 cartoons]
- Package 21
  - Mom 'n' Pop [214 cartoons]
    - 1928
    - March 2, 3, 5, 7-10, 12-17, 19-24, 26-31
    - April 2-7, 9-14, 16, 17, 28, 30
    - May 1-4, 28-31
    - June 1, 2, 4, 5, 8, 9, 11-15, 19-23, 25-28
    - July 2-7, 11-14, 16-21, 23-28, 30, 31
    - August 1-4, 6-11, 13-18, 20-25, 27-31
    - September 1, 3-8, 11-15, 17-22, 24-29
    - Oct 1, 2, 4-6, 8-13, 15-18, 20, 22-27, 29-31
    - November 1-3, 5-10, 12-14, 21, 27-30
    - December 1, 3-7, 10-12, 14, 15, 17-20, 22, 24-27
    - 1929
    - May 25
    - July 26
    - Sept. 15
    - 1931
    - April 1-3, 6,7
- Package 22
  - Sissy (1942-1945?) [88 items]
    - April 28, 29
    - May 1-5, 8-13, 15, 18-20, 23, 25-27, 29-31
    - June 2, 3, 5-10, 12-15, 17-22, 24, 27-29
    - July 1, 3, 4, 7, 8, 10-15, 24-29
    - August 1-5, 8, 9, 12, 14-18, 22-26
    - March 17 [Sunday 1945?)
    - Proofs [5 pages]
- Package 23
  - Women with a Gun [painting]
- Package 24
  - Miscellaneous drawings and cartoons [7 items]
- Package 25
  - Them Were the Days